Finding Aid for David E. Cole papers, 1951-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series contains correspondence written and received by Cole during his affiliation with the University of Michigan. The series is arranged into two subseries by chronological and alphabetical order. The chronological subseries dates from 1979 to 2000 and contains correspondence from Cole's time as the Director of the Office for the Study of Automotive Transportation (OSAT). This correspondence covers a variety of subjects concerning OSAT, such as automotive projects, seminars (including the Traverse City Management Briefing Seminar), staffing/employment, funding and automotive issues and research. The alphabetical subseries is arranged by last name or company and is divided into two groups by date, which is how the subseries was originally arranged. It seems that this subseries focuses more on Cole's professional activities outside of OSAT. Correspondence can be found throughout the collection within other series.
  - Chronological
    - 1978 (Box 24)
    - 1979, 3 folders (Box 24)
    - 1980, 12 folders (Box 24)
    - 1981
      - January-March, 1981, 3 folders (Box 24)
      - April-December, 1981, 9 folders (Box 25)
    - 1982, 12 folders (Box 25)
    - 1983, 12 folders (Box 25)
    - 1984
      - January-April, 1984, 4 folders (Box 25)
      - May-December, 1984, 8 folders (Box 26)
    - 1985, 12 folders (Box 26)
    - 1986, 12 folders
      - January-October, 1986, 10 folders (Box 26)
      - November-December, 1986, 2 folders (Box 27)
    - 1987, 12 folders (Box 27)
    - 1988, 12 folders (Box 27)
    - 1989
      - January-May, 1989, 5 folders (Box 27)
      - June-December, 1989, 7 folders (Box 28)
    - 1990, 12 folders (Box 28)
    - 1991, 12 folders (Box 28)
    - 1992, 12 folders (Box 28)
    - 1993, 12 folders (Box 29)
    - 1994, 12 folders (Box 29)
    - 1995, 12 folders (Box 29)
    - 1996
      - January-May, 1996, 5 folders (Box 29)
      - June-December, 1996, 7 folders (Box 30)
    - 1997, 12 folders (Box 30)
    - 1998, 12 folders (Box 30)
    - 1999
      - January-June, 1999, 6 folders (Box 30)
      - July-December, 1999, 6 folders (Box 31)
    - 2000, 12 folders (Box 31)
    - Undated (Box 31)
  - Alphabetical
    - 1960s-1970s
      - A-V, 11 folders (Box 31)
      - W-Z (Box 32)
    - 1980s-1990s
      - A-N, 15 folders (Box 32)
      - O-Z, 8 folders (Box 33)
- Research
  The Research series documents Cole's consulting work and research activities. The Consulting subseries contains information on Cole's consulting work for various companies. Cole provided consulting services for Bendix as part of their Technical Advisory Board. He was a member of the Chevrolet-Pontiac-Canada Group (CPC) Supplier Council Joint Committee and also their College of Engineering Board. This subseries is separate from the Company Files because this division reflects the original arrangement of the collection. The Conference and Seminars subseries documents events that Cole attended or helped to plan. For more documentation on conferences, please see the Speaking Engagements series. Cole's research interests included the Wankel engine, which was an internal combustion engine with a rotary design invented by German engineer Felix Wankel. The Wankel Engine subseries contains correspondence, reports, publications and clippings, and information on the 1972 Wankel Engine Seminar in Traverse City.
  - Consulting
    - AISI (American Iron and Steel Institute), 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 33)
    - Aluminum Association Advisory Committee, 1983-1985 (Box 33)
    - Bendix
      - Technical Advisory Board (TAB), 1980-1981 (Box 33)
      - Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 33)
      - Automotive Group Engineering Conference, 1982 (Box 33)
      - Planning (Box 33)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 33)
    - Chevrolet-Pontiac-Canada Group (CPC)
      - College of Engineering Board, 1986-1987 (Box 34)
      - Supplier Council, 1987-1989 (Box 34)
    - French scientific attaché, 1980-1985 (Box 34)
    - Small Supplier Forum, 1980s (Box 34)
  - Conferences and Seminars
    - 5th International Automotive Propulsion Systems Symposium (Box 34)
    - Alternative Power Plan Conference and Low Pollution Power Plants Seminar (Box 34)
    - American Academy of Arts and Science Seminar, 1991 (Box 34)
    - Automotive Industry in Asia, 1995; 1997 (Box 34)
    - Automotive Planning Seminar, Chrysler Center, 1980 (Box 34)
    - Automotive Trends, American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1983 (Box 34)
    - Canada's Auto Industry Conference (Box 34)
    - Conference on Plastics, presentation by Harbeck, 1982 (Box 34)
    - Department of Energy (DOE) Contractors Meeting, 1983-1984 (Box 34)
    - Detroit Institute of Ophthalmology -- "Eyes on Design" and "The Eye and the Auto,", 2002-2003 (Box 34)
    - "Development of High Technology Industries in Michigan" Conference, 1981 (Box 34)
    - Engineering Society of Detroit (EDS) -- OEM/Supplier Conference, 1982 (Box 34)
    - ISATA (International Symposium on Automotive Technology and Automation), 1990s (Box 34)
    - Manufacturer/Supplier Symposium, 1983-1984 (Box 34)
    - New York Academy of Medicine Symposium, 1980 (Box 35)
    - SITEV (International Exhibition of Suppliers to the Vehicle Industry)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 35)
      - 1982 (Box 35)
    - US-China Automotive Component and Equipment Suppliers Conference, 1997 (Box 35)
    - World Economy Forum (Box 35)
    - World Petroleum Conference, 1983 (Box 35)
    - Miscellaneous (includes slides) (Box 35)
  - Wankel Engine, 1960s-1990s
    - Engineering Society of Detroit (ESD) program, 1973-1974 (Box 35)
    - Europe (trip to Germany to discuss the rotary engine), 1973 (Box 35)
    - German film trip (Box 35)
    - Scientific American (Box 35)
    - Saturday Evening Post (Box 35)
    - Correspondence, 1970s (Box 35)
    - Reports and notes, including the 1972 Wankel Engine Seminar at Traverse City, 1971-1972 (Box 35)
    - Engine pictures (Box 35)
    - Rotary engine plan (Box 35)
    - W.E. Hutton and Co. (Box 35)
    - Speech at Chicago Chemical Specialties on the car, 1990 (Box 35)
    - Course on low emission power plan systems taught by Cole and Bolt, 1972 (Box 35)
    - Patent information (Box 35)
    - Engine information in German (Box 35)
    - Mercedes-Benz Press (Box 35)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 35)
    - Publications and clippings
      - 1960s (Box 35)
      - 1970s (Box 36)
      - 1980s (Box 36)
      - 1990s (Box 36)
      - Undated (Box 36)
      - Ward's Wankel Report, 1972-1973 (Box 36)
      - Wankel clippings, 1960s-1970s (Box 36)
      - Wankel clippings, 1970s (Box 36)
      - Clippings and miscellaneous, 1970s (Box 36)
      - Books
        - Rotary Piston Machines (possibly signed by Wankel), 1965 (Box 36)
        - The Wankel RC Engine (signed by author), 1968 (Box 36)
        - The Wankel Engine (signed by author), 1971 (Box 37)
        - The Automobile-Energy and the Environment, 1974 (Box 37)
        - Mazda Rotary Engine Manual (Box 37)
      - Wankel Engines A to Z (signed by author), 1973 (Box 37)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Outboard Marine Company (OMC) research project (Box 37)
    - "Notes on Suspension by Maurice Olley,", 1961 (Box 37)
- Speaking Engagements
  The Speaking Engagements series documents Cole's activities as a keynote speaker, public lecturer and panel member at various conferences and seminars. Materials include Cole's presentations and speeches, although the majority of the series is composed of correspondence and conference materials. Cole was a speaker at a variety of conferences, as well as at other venues. The series is arranged chronologically, and contains material from 1972 to 2000.
  - 1972, 2 folders (Box 37)
  - 1973, 3 folders (Box 37)
  - 1974 (Box 37)
  - 1975 (Box 37)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 37)
  - Automotive Leasing Associated Midyear Meeting, 1980 (Box 37)
  - 1981 February-September (Box 37)
  - December (includes photo), October 1981 (Box 37)
  - 1982 (Box 37)
  - 1983
    - Arvid Jouppi Meeting (Box 37)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 37)
  - 1984
    - Engineering Society of Detroit (ESD) Computer Graphics (Box 37)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 37)
  - 1985 (Box 38)
  - 1986 (Box 38)
  - 1987
    - International Iron and Steel Institute (IISI), 1987 (Box 38)
    - Miscellaneous, 1987 (Box 38)
  - 1988
    - International Nonwoven Fabric Conference, 1988 (Box 38)
    - Miscellaneous, 1988 (Box 38)
  - 1990
    - SAE Passenger Car Meeting, 1990 (Box 38)
    - WJR Automotive Report, 1990 (Box 38)
    - Miscellaneous, 1990 (Box 38)
  - 1991, 3 folders (Box 38)
  - 1992, 3 folders (Box 38)
  - 1993, 4 folders (Box 39)
  - 1994, 4 folders (Box 39)
  - 1995, 5 folders (Box 39)
  - 1996
    - Automotive News World Congress, 1995-1996 (Box 39)
    - QAD, 1996 (Box 39)
    - Miscellaneous, 1996; 4 folders (Box 39)
    - Miscellaneous, 1996; 2 folders (Box 40)
  - 1997, 4 folders (Box 40)
  - 1998, 5 folders (Box 40)
  - 1999
    - Global Environment Conference, 1999 (Box 40)
    - Miscellaneous, 1999 (Box 40)
  - 2000 (Box 41)
- Publications, Papers and Clippings
  The Publications, Papers and Clippings series contains material authored by Cole, articles about Cole, and publications documenting the automotive industry. The Publications and Papers subseries contains research papers, reports and magazines focused on the automotive industry, as well as Cole's dissertation from 1966. Publications on the Wankel engine can be found in the Research series. The Clippings subseries contains newspaper articles that feature Cole or that were written by him, in addition to articles centered on the automotive industry. In the clippings by subject, the folder headings in quotations represent original headings.
  - Publications and Papers
    - 1950s (Box 41)
    - 1960s (Box 41)
      (Includes dissertation from 1966)
    - 1970-1975 (Box 41)
    - 1976-1979 (Box 42)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 42)
    - 1982-1984 (Box 42)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 42)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 42)
    - 1989 (Box 42)
    - 1990 (Box 42)
    - 1991 (Box 42)
    - 1992 (Box 42)
    - 1993 (Box 43)
    - 1994 (Box 43)
    - 1995 (Box 43)
    - 1996 (Box 43)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 43)
    - 1999 (Box 43)
    - 2000 (Box 43)
    - 2001-2002 (Box 44)
    - Undated (Box 44)
    - Publications by subject
      - 1990 Family Car article for Galileo Magazine, 1980 (Box 44)
      - "Automotive book for U-M Press,", 1981 (Box 44)
      - Curtiss-Wright paper (includes photos), 1969-1971 (Box 44)
      - Fuel economy book, written in conjunction with Hilliard, 1980-1981 (Box 44)
      - World Book Encyclopedia, 1980s-1990s (Box 44)
  - Clippings
    - 1980-1984 (Box 44)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 44)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 44)
    - 1989 (Box 44)
    - 1990 (Box 44)
    - 1991 (Box 44)
    - 1992, 2 folders (Box 45)
    - 1993 (Box 45)
    - 1994 (Box 45)
    - 1995 (Box 45)
    - 1996 (Box 45)
    - 1997 (Box 46)
    - 1998, 2 folders (Box 46)
    - 1999 (Box 46)
    - 2000 (Box 46)
    - Undated (Box 46)
    - Clippings by subject
      - Delphi, 1972-1982 (Box 47)
      - "Delphi News Clippings,", 1992 (Box 47)
      - "Detroit News Article,", August 1987 (Box 47)
      - "ERIM,", 1979-1980 (Box 47)
      - "Faculty -- College of Engineering,", 1980-1982 (Box 47)
      - "News Releases on OSAT & Dave Cole,", 1979-1984 (scattered) (Box 47)
      - "Press Releases" (Box 47)
      - International and American automotive industries, 1983 (Box 47)
      - Small cars and miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 47)
      - Future cars and miscellaneous (Box 47)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series contains Cole's subject files. Topics include energy, quality and the electric vehicle. For the "Measuring Cost and Value" paper and management highlights of the Product Development Study, please see Sigma Associates in the Company Files series.
  - Automotive Body -- Training and Technology Center, 1990s (Box 47)
  - Auto Safety, 1992 undated (Box 47)
  - Economic Significance of the Industry
    - Industrial ecology seminar, 1994 (Box 47)
    - OSAT, 1992 (Box 47)
  - Electric vehicle
    - University of California, Berkeley, 1986 (Box 47)
    - Miscellaneous, 1991; 1999 (Box 47)
  - Energy, 1970s-1980s (Box 47)
  - FISTIA, 1990s (Box 47)
  - Marks' Handbook, 1993; 1995 (Box 47)
  - Partnership for a New Generation of Vehicles Marketplace Acceptance (PNGV) Study, 1990s (Box 47)
  - Product Development Study (Auto/Steel Partnership Program)
    - "Product Development Systems" by the Industrial Development Division, 1990 (Box 47)
    - Supplier conference and dissertation proposal, 1991 (Box 47)
  - Quality, 1990s (Box 47)
  - Stirling Thermal Motors, Inc. (Box 47)
  - University of Michigan Flint project, 1990s (Box 47)
- Audio-Visual Material
  The Audio-Visual Material series contains Beta tapes, VHS tapes and one audiocassette. The majority of the series consists of tapes from Cole's Mechanical Engineering courses.
  - ME (Mechanical Engineering) 438 course, Beta Tapes
    - 10/18/1990 (Box 48)
    - 10/23/1990 (Box 48)
    - 10/30/1990 (Box 48)
    - 11/1/1990 (Box 48)
    - 11/6/1990 (Box 48)
    - 11/8/1990 (Box 48)
  - ME (Mechanical Engineering) 458, VHS Tapes
    - 2/19/1991 (Box 48)
    - 2/21/1991 (Box 48)
    - 3/12/1991 (Box 48)
    - 3/14/1991 (Box 48)
    - 4/2/1991 (Box 48)
    - 4/16/1991 (Box 48)
  - Miscellaneous, VHS Tapes
    - "Detroit Arsenal Tank Plant, 16:45" (Box 48)
    - "Focus: Hope, An Investment in People" (Box 48)
  - "Bendix :60 'Brake' Spot", audio-cassette (Box 48)
Related Material
The Bentley Historical Library also holds some records of the University of Michigan Office for the Study of Automotive Transportation (OSAT).